<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docarticle/xml/4.5/docarticlex.dtd" [
]>
<section id="Tuned">
	<title>Tuned and ktune</title>
	
	<para>
		<application>Tuned</application> is a daemon that monitors the use of system components and dynamically tunes system settings based on that monitoring information. Dynamic tuning accounts for the way that various system components are used differently throughout the uptime for any given system. For example, the hard drive is used heavily during startup and login, but is barely used later when a user might mainly work with applications like OpenOffice or email clients. Similarly, the CPU and network devices are used differently at different times. <application>Tuned</application> monitors the activity of these components and reacts to changes in their use. 
	</para>
	<para>
		As a practical example, consider a typical office workstation. Most of the time, the Ethernet network interface will be very inactive. Only a few emails will go in and out every once in a while or some web pages might be loaded. For those kinds of loads, the network interface doesn't have to run at full speed all the time, as it does by default. <application>Tuned</application> has a monitoring and tuning plugin for network devices that can detect that low activity and then automatically lower the speed of that interface, typically resulting in lower power usage. If activity on the interface increases drastically for a longer period of time, for example because a DVD image is being downloaded or an email with a large attachment is opened, <application>tuned</application> detects this and sets the interface speed to maximum to offer the best performance while the activity level is so high. This principle is used for the other plugins for CPU and hard disks as well.
	</para>
	<para>
		Network devices are not configured to behave this way by default because speed changes can take several seconds to take effect and therefore directly and visibly impact the user experience. Similar considerations apply for the CPU and hard drive tuning plugins. When a hard drive has been spun down, it can take several seconds for it to spin up again which results in an observed lack of responsiveness of the system during that period. The latency side effect is smallest for the CPU plugin, but it is still at least measurable, though hardly noticeable by a user.
	</para>
	<para>
		Alongside of <application>tuned</application> we now also offer <application>ktune</application>. <application>Ktune</application> was originally a framework and service to optimize the performance of a machine for a specific use cases. Since then, <application>ktune</application> has improved to such a degree that we now use it as the static part of our general tuning framework. It is mainly used in the different predefined profiles described in <xref linkend="tuned-adm"/>.
	</para>

	<para>
		Install the <package>tuned</package> package and its associated <application>systemtap</application> scripts with the command:
	</para>
<screen><command>yum install tuned</command></screen>
	<para>
		Installing the <package>tuned</package> package also sets up a sample configuration file at <filename>/etc/tuned.conf</filename> and activates the default profile.
	</para>
	<para>
		Start <application>tuned</application> by running:
	</para>
<screen><command>service tuned start</command></screen>
	<para>
		To start <application>tuned</application> every time the machine boots, run:
	</para>
<screen><command>chkconfig tuned on</command></screen>
	<para>
		<application>Tuned</application> itself has additional options that you can use when you run it manually. The available options are:
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><option>-d</option></term>
			<term><option>--daemon</option></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					start <application>tuned</application> as a daemon instead of in the foreground.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><option>-c</option></term>
			<term><option>--conffile</option></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					use a configuration file with the specified name and path, for example, <literal>--conffile=/etc/tuned2.conf</literal>. The default is <filename>/etc/tuned.conf</filename>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><option>-D</option></term>
			<term><option>--debug</option></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					use the highest level of logging.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<section id="The_tuned.conf_file">
		<title>The <filename>tuned.conf</filename> file</title>
		<para>
			The <filename>tuned.conf</filename> file contains configuration settings for <application>tuned</application>. By default, it is located at <filename>/etc/tuned.conf</filename>, but you can specify a different name and location by starting <application>tuned</application> with the <option>--conffile</option> option.
		</para>
		<para>
			The config file must always contain a <literal>[main]</literal> section that defines the general parameters for <application>tuned</application>. The file then contains a section for each plugin.
		</para>
		<para>
			The <literal>[main]</literal> section contains the following options:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>interval</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the interval at which <application>tuned</application> should monitor and tune the system, in seconds. The default value is <literal>10</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>verbose</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies whether output should be verbose. The default value is <literal>False</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>logging</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies the minimum priority of messages to be logged. In descending order, allowable values are: <literal>critical</literal>, <literal>error</literal>, <literal>warning</literal>, <literal>info</literal>, and <literal>debug</literal>. The default value is <literal>info</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>logging_disable</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies the maximum priority of messages to be logged; any messages with this priority or lower will not be logged. In descending order, allowable values are: <literal>critical</literal>, <literal>error</literal>, <literal>warning</literal>, <literal>info</literal>, and <literal>debug</literal>. The value <literal>notset</literal> disables this option.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			Each plugin has its own section, specified with the name of the plugin in square brackets; for example: <literal>[CPUTuning]</literal>. Each plugin can have its own options, but the following apply to all plugins:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>enabled</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies whether the plugin is enabled or not. The default value is <literal>True</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>verbose</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies whether output should be verbose. If not set for this plugin, the value is inherited from <literal>[main]</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><option>logging</option></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						specifies the minimum priority of messages to be logged. If not set for this plugin, the value is inherited from <literal>[main]</literal>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
			A sample config file follows:
		</para>
<programlisting>[main]
interval=10
pidfile=/var/run/tuned.pid
logging=info
logging_disable=notset

# Disk monitoring section

[DiskMonitor]
enabled=True
logging=debug

# Disk tuning section

[DiskTuning]
enabled=True
hdparm=False
alpm=False
logging=debug

# Net monitoring section

[NetMonitor]
enabled=True
logging=debug

# Net tuning section

[NetTuning]
enabled=True
logging=debug

# CPU monitoring section

[CPUMonitor]
# Enabled or disable the plugin. Default is True. Any other value
# disables it.
enabled=True

# CPU tuning section

[CPUTuning]
# Enabled or disable the plugin. Default is True. Any other value
# disables it.
enabled=True</programlisting>
	<para>
    The CPU tuning plugin recently added support for the Super Hybrid Engine (SHE), as found on some Asus EEEPCs. If you are using this engine, you can enable SHE support by adding <option>eeefsb=True</option> into the <literal>[CPUTuning]</literal> section of <filename>tuned.conf</filename>. It will automatically downclock your FSB and save power while on idle, returning to normal speed when the load increases significantly. This functionality is enabled by default in the <literal>laptop-battery-powersave</literal> profile.
  </para>
  </section>
	<section id="tuned-adm">
		<title>Tuned-adm</title>
		<para>
			Often, a detailed audit and analysis of a system can be very time consuming and might not be worth the few extra watts you might be able to save by doing so. Previously, the only alternative was simply to use the defaults. Therefore, Fedora&nbsp;&PRODVER; includes separate profiles for specific use cases as an alternative between those two extremes, together with the <application>tuned-adm</application> tool that allows you to switch between these profiles easily at the command line. Fedora&nbsp;&PRODVER; includes a number of predefined profiles for typical use cases that you can simply select and activate with the <command>tuned-adm</command> command, but you can also create, modify or delete profiles yourself.
		</para>
		<para>
			To list all available profiles and identify the current active profile, run:
		</para>
<screen><command>tuned-adm list</command></screen>
		<para>
			To only display the currently active profile, run:
		</para>
<screen><command>tuned-adm active</command></screen>
		<para>
			To switch to one of the available profiles, run:
		</para>
<screen><command>tuned-adm profile <replaceable>profile_name</replaceable></command></screen>
		<para>
			for example:
		</para>
<screen><command>tuned-adm profile server-powersave</command></screen>
		<para>
			To disable all tuning:
		</para>
<screen><command>tuned-adm off</command></screen>
		<para>
		  When you first install <application>tuned</application>, the <literal>balanced</literal> profile will be active. The following predefined profiles are available after installing <package>tuned</package>:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
		  
		<varlistentry>
				<term>balanced</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the default power-saving profile. It enables CPU and disk plugins of <application>tuned</application> and activates the <command>ondemand</command> governor.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>powersave</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a profile for maximum power saving performance. It enables USB autosuspend, WiFi power saving, and ALPM power saving for SATA host adapters (refer to <xref linkend="ALPM"/>). It also schedules multi-core power savings for systems with a low wakeup rate and activates the <command>ondemand</command> governor.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		  
			<varlistentry>
				<term>throughput-performance</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a server profile for typical throughput performance tuning. It disables <application>tuned</application> and <application>ktune</application> power saving mechanisms, enables <application>sysctl</application> settings that improve the throughput performance of your disk and network I/O, and switches to the <application>deadline scheduler</application>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>latency-performance</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a server profile for typical latency performance tuning. it disables <application>tuned</application> and <application>ktune</application> power saving mechanisms and enables <application>sysctl</application> settings that improve the latency performance of your network I/O.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>virtual-guest</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a profile designed for virtual guests based on the enterprise-storage profile that, among other tasks, decreases virtual memory swappiness.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
			<varlistentry>
				<term>virtual-host</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a profile designed for virtual hosts based on the enterprise-storage profile that, among other tasks, decreases virtual memory swappiness and is more aggressive in its writeback of dirty pages.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			
		      </variablelist>
		      
		      <para>
			Additional predefined profiles are available by installing the <package>tuned-profiles-compat</package> package:
		      </para>
		      
		      <variablelist>
		  
			<varlistentry>
				<term>default</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						this has the lowest impact on power saving of the available profiles and only enables CPU and disk plugins of <application>tuned</application>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>desktop-powersave</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a power-saving profile directed at desktop systems. Enables ALPM power saving for SATA host adapters (refer to <xref linkend="ALPM"/>) as well as the CPU, Ethernet, and disk plugins of <application>tuned</application>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>server-powersave</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a power-saving profile directed at server systems. Enables ALPM powersaving for SATA host adapters and activates the CPU and disk plugins of <application>tuned</application>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>laptop-ac-powersave</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a medium-impact power-saving profile directed at laptops running on AC. Enables ALPM powersaving for SATA host adapters, Wi-Fi power saving, as well as the CPU, Ethernet, and disk plugins of <application>tuned</application>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>laptop-battery-powersave</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a high-impact power-saving profile directed at laptops running on battery. It activates all power saving mechanisms from the previous profiles, plus it enables the multi-core power-savings scheduler for low wakeup systems and makes sure that the ondemand governor is active and that AC97 audio power-saving is enabled. On compatible Asus EEEPCs, it enables SHE support in the CPU tuning plugin. You can use this profile to save the maximum amount of power on any kind of system, not only laptops on battery power. The trade-off for this profile is a noticeable impact on performance, specifically latency of disk and network I/O.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>spindown-disk</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a power-saving profile for machines with classic HDDs to maximize spindown time. It disables the <application>tuned</application> power savings mechanism, disables USB autosuspend, disables Bluetooth, enables Wi-Fi power saving, disables logs syncing, increases disk write-back time, and lowers disk swappiness. All partitions are remounted with <option>noatime</option>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>enterprise-storage</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						a server profile directed at enterprise-class storage, maximizing I/O throughput. It activates the same settings as the <literal>throughput-performance</literal> profile, multiplies readahead settings, and disables barriers on non-root and non-boot partitions.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		
		<para>
			All the profiles are stored in separate subdirectories under <filename>/etc/tune-profiles</filename>. So <filename>/etc/tune-profiles/desktop-powersave</filename> contains all the necessary files and settings for that profile. Each of these directories contains up to four files:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><filename>tuned.conf</filename></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the configuration for the tuned service to be active for this profile.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><filename>sysctl.ktune</filename></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the <application>sysctl</application> settings used by <application>ktune</application>. The format is identical to the <filename>/etc/sysconfig/sysctl</filename> file (refer to the <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysctl</refentrytitle></citerefentry> and <citerefentry><refentrytitle>sysctl.conf</refentrytitle></citerefentry> man pages).
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><filename>ktune.sysconfig</filename></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						the configuration file of ktune itself, typically <filename>/etc/sysconfig/ktune</filename>.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term><filename>ktune.sh</filename></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						an <application>init</application>-style shell script used by the <application>ktune</application> service which can run specific commands during system startup to tune the system.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		
		<para>
			The easiest way to start a new profile is to copy an existing one. The <literal>laptop-battery-powersave</literal> profile contains a very rich set of tunings already and is therefore a useful starting point. Simply copy the whole directory to the new profile name like this:
		</para>
<screen><command>cp -a /etc/tune-profiles/laptop-battery-powersave/ /etc/tune-profiles/myprofile</command></screen>
		<para>
			Modify any of the files in the new profile to match your personal requirements. 
		</para>
	</section>
</section>
